قُلِ اللَّهُمَّ مَالِكَ الْمُلْكِ تُؤْتِي الْمُلْكَ مَن تَشَاءُ وَتَنزِعُ الْمُلْكَ مِمَّن تَشَاءُ
Say, "O Allah, Owner of Sovereignty, You give sovereignty to whom You will and You take sovereignty away from whom You will.
وَتُعِزُّ مَن تَشَاءُ وَتُذِلُّ مَن تَشَاءُ ۖ بِيَدِكَ الْخَيْرُ ۖ إِنَّكَ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ - 3:26
You honor whom You will and You humble whom You will. In Your hand is [all] good. Indeed, You are over all things competent.
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the cursed Satan
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the name of Allah, The All-Merciful, The Ever-Merciful
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ يَكْفُرُونَ بِآيَاتِ اللَّهِ وَيَقْتُلُونَ النَّبِيِّينَ بِغَيْرِ حَقٍّ وَيَقْتُلُونَ الَّذِينَ يَأْمُرُونَ بِالْقِسْطِ
Those who disbelieve in the signs of Allah and kill the prophets without right and kill those who order justice from among the people
وَيَقْتُلُونَ الَّذِينَ يَأْمُرُونَ بِالْقِسْطِ مِنَ النَّاسِ فَبَشِّرْهُم بِعَذَابٍ أَلِيمٍ - 3:21
and kill those who order justice from among the people - give them tidings of a painful punishment.
أُولَٰئِكَ الَّذِينَ حَبِطَتْ أَعْمَالُهُمْ فِي الدُّنْيَا وَالْآخِرَةِ وَمَا لَهُم مِّن نَّاصِرِينَ - 3:22
They are the ones whose deeds have become worthless in this world and the Hereafter, and for them there will be no helpers.
أَلَمْ تَرَ إِلَى الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا نَصِيبًا مِّنَ الْكِتَابِ
Do you not consider, [O Muhammad], those who were given a portion of the Scripture?
يُدْعَوْنَ إِلَىٰ كِتَابِ اللَّهِ لِيَحْكُمَ بَيْنَهُمْ ثُمَّ يَتَوَلَّىٰ فَرِيقٌ مِّنْهُمْ وَهُم مُّعْرِضُونَ - 3:23
They are invited to the Scripture of Allah that it should arbitrate between them; then a party of them turns away, and they are refusing.
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ قَالُوا لَن تَمَسَّنَا النَّارُ إِلَّا أَيَّامًا مَّعْدُودَاتٍ ۖ
That is because they say, "Never will the Fire touch us except for [a few] numbered days,"
وَغَرَّهُمْ فِي دِينِهِم مَّا كَانُوا يَفْتَرُونَ - 3:24
and [because] they were deluded in their religion by what they were inventing.
فَكَيْفَ إِذَا جَمَعْنَاهُمْ لِيَوْمٍ لَّا رَيْبَ فِيهِ
So how will it be when We assemble them for a Day about which there is no doubt?
وَوُفِّيَتْ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ مَّا كَسَبَتْ
And each soul will be compensated [in full for] what it earned,
فَكَيْفَ إِذَا جَمَعْنَاهُمْ لِيَوْمٍ لَّا رَيْبَ فِيهِ
So how will it be when We assemble them for a Day about which there is no doubt?
وَوُفِّيَتْ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ مَّا كَسَبَتْ وَهُمْ لَا يُظْلَمُونَ - 3:25
And each soul will be compensated [in full for] what it earned, and they will not be wronged.
قُلِ اللَّهُمَّ مَالِكَ الْمُلْكِ تُؤْتِي الْمُلْكَ مَن تَشَاءُ وَتَنزِعُ الْمُلْكَ مِمَّن تَشَاءُ
Say, "O Allah, Owner of Sovereignty, You give sovereignty to whom You will and You take sovereignty away from whom You will.
وَتُعِزُّ مَن تَشَاءُ وَتُذِلُّ مَن تَشَاءُ ۖ بِيَدِكَ الْخَيْرُ ۖ إِنَّكَ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ - 3:26
You honor whom You will and You humble whom You will. In Your hand is [all] good. Indeed, You are over all things competent.
تُولِجُ اللَّيْلَ فِي النَّهَارِ وَتُولِجُ النَّهَارَ فِي اللَّيْلِ ۖ وَتُخْرِجُ الْحَيَّ مِنَ الْمَيِّتِ
You cause the night to enter the day, and You cause the day to enter the night; and You bring the living out of the dead,
وَتُخْرِجُ الْحَيَّ مِنَ الْمَيِّتِ وَتُخْرِجُ الْمَيِّتَ مِنَ الْحَيِّ ۖ وَتَرْزُقُ مَن تَشَاءُ بِغَيْرِ حِسَابٍ - 3:27
and You bring the living out of the dead, and You bring the dead out of the living. And You give provision to whom You will without account."
لَّا يَتَّخِذِ الْمُؤْمِنُونَ الْكَافِرِينَ أَوْلِيَاءَ مِن دُونِ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ ۖ
Let not believers take disbelievers as allies rather than believers.
وَمَن يَفْعَلْ ذَٰلِكَ فَلَيْسَ مِنَ اللَّهِ فِي شَيْءٍ إِلَّا أَن تَتَّقُوا مِنْهُمْ تُقَاةً ۗ
And whoever [of you] does that has nothing with Allah, except when taking precaution against them in prudence.
وَيُحَذِّرُكُمُ اللَّهُ نَفْسَهُ ۗ وَإِلَى اللَّهِ الْمَصِيرُ - 3:28
And Allah warns you of Himself, and to Allah is the [final] destination.
قُلْ إِن تُخْفُوا مَا فِي صُدُورِكُمْ أَوْ تُبْدُوهُ يَعْلَمْهُ اللَّهُ ۗ
Say, "Whether you conceal what is in your breasts or reveal it, Allah knows it.
وَيَعْلَمُ مَا فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَا فِي الْأَرْضِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ - 3:29
And He knows that which is in the heavens and that which is on the earth. And Allah is over all things competent.
يَوْمَ تَجِدُ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ مَّا عَمِلَتْ مِنْ خَيْرٍ مُّحْضَرًا وَمَا عَمِلَتْ مِن سُوءٍ
The Day every soul will find what it has done of good present [before it] and what it has done of evil,
وَمَا عَمِلَتْ مِن سُوءٍ تَوَدُّ لَوْ أَنَّ بَيْنَهَا وَبَيْنَهُ أَمَدًا بَعِيدًا ۗ
and what it has done of evil, it will wish that between itself and that [evil] was a great distance.
وَيُحَذِّرُكُمُ اللَّهُ نَفْسَهُ ۗ وَاللَّهُ رَءُوفٌ بِالْعِبَادِ - 3:30
And Allah warns you of Himself, and Allah is Kind to [His] servants."
قُلْ إِن كُنتُمْ تُحِبُّونَ اللَّهَ فَاتَّبِعُونِي يُحْبِبْكُمُ اللَّهُ وَيَغْفِرْ لَكُمْ ذُنُوبَكُمْ ۗ وَاللَّهُ غَفُورٌ رَّحِيمٌ - 3:31
Say, "If you should love Allah, then follow me, [so] Allah will love you and forgive you your sins. And Allah is Forgiving and Merciful."
قُلْ أَطِيعُوا اللَّهَ وَالرَّسُولَ ۖ فَإِن تَوَلَّوْا فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يُحِبُّ الْكَافِرِينَ - 3:32
Say, "Obey Allah and the Messenger." But if they turn away - then indeed, Allah does not like the disbelievers.
إِنَّ اللَّهَ اصْطَفَىٰ آدَمَ وَنُوحًا وَآلَ إِبْرَاهِيمَ وَآلَ عِمْرَانَ عَلَى الْعَالَمِينَ - 3:33
Indeed, Allah chose Adam and Noah and the family of Abraham and the family of 'Imran over the worlds -
ذُرِّيَّةً بَعْضُهَا مِن بَعْضٍ ۗ وَاللَّهُ سَمِيعٌ عَلِيمٌ - 3:34
Descendants, some of them from others. And Allah is Hearing and Knowing.
إِذْ قَالَتِ امْرَأَتُ عِمْرَانَ
[Mention, O Muhammad], when the wife of 'Imran said,
رَبِّ إِنِّي نَذَرْتُ لَكَ مَا فِي بَطْنِي مُحَرَّرًا فَتَقَبَّلْ مِنِّي ۖ
"My Lord, indeed I have pledged to You what is in my womb, consecrated [for Your service], so accept this from me.
فَتَقَبَّلْ مِنِّي ۖ إِنَّكَ أَنتَ السَّمِيعُ الْعَلِيمُ - 3:35
so accept this from me. Indeed, You are the Hearing, the Knowing."
فَلَمَّا وَضَعَتْهَا قَالَتْ رَبِّ إِنِّي وَضَعْتُهَا أُنثَىٰ وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ
But when she delivered her, she said, "My Lord, I have delivered a female." And Allah was most knowing of what she delivered,
وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ وَإِنِّي سَمَّيْتُهَا مَرْيَمَ
And the male is not like the female. And I have named her Mary,
وَإِنِّي سَمَّيْتُهَا مَرْيَمَ وَإِنِّي أُعِيذُهَا بِكَ وَذُرِّيَّتَهَا مِنَ الشَّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيمِ - 3:36
And I have named her Mary, and I seek refuge for her in You and [for] her descendants from Satan, the expelled [from the mercy of Allah ]."
فَتَقَبَّلَهَا رَبُّهَا بِقَبُولٍ حَسَنٍ وَأَنبَتَهَا نَبَاتًا حَسَنًا
So her Lord accepted her with good acceptance and caused her to grow in a good manner
وَكَفَّلَهَا زَكَرِيَّا ۖ كُلَّمَا دَخَلَ عَلَيْهَا زَكَرِيَّا الْمِحْرَابَ وَجَدَ عِندَهَا رِزْقًا ۖ
and put her in the care of Zechariah. Every time Zechariah entered upon her in the prayer chamber, he found with her provision.
وَجَدَ عِندَهَا رِزْقًا ۖ قَالَ يَا مَرْيَمُ أَنَّىٰ لَكِ هَٰذَا ۖ
He found with her provision. He said, "O Mary, from where is this [coming] to you?"
قَالَتْ هُوَ مِنْ عِندِ اللَّهِ ۖ إِنَّ اللَّهَ يَرْزُقُ مَن يَشَاءُ بِغَيْرِ حِسَابٍ - 3:37
She said, "It is from Allah . Indeed, Allah provides for whom He wills without account."
هُنَالِكَ دَعَا زَكَرِيَّا رَبَّهُ ۖ قَالَ رَبِّ هَبْ لِي مِن لَّدُنكَ ذُرِّيَّةً طَيِّبَةً ۖ
At that, Zechariah called upon his Lord, saying, "My Lord, grant me from Yourself a good offspring.
قَالَ رَبِّ هَبْ لِي مِن لَّدُنكَ ذُرِّيَّةً طَيِّبَةً ۖ إِنَّكَ سَمِيعُ الدُّعَاءِ - 3:38
"My Lord, grant me from Yourself a good offspring. Indeed, You are the Hearer of supplication."
فَنَادَتْهُ الْمَلَائِكَةُ وَهُوَ قَائِمٌ يُصَلِّي فِي الْمِحْرَابِ أَنَّ اللَّهَ يُبَشِّرُكَ
So the angels called him while he was standing in prayer in the chamber, "Indeed, Allah gives you good tidings
أَنَّ اللَّهَ يُبَشِّرُكَ بِيَحْيَىٰ مُصَدِّقًا بِكَلِمَةٍ مِّنَ اللَّهِ وَسَيِّدًا وَحَصُورًا
"Indeed, Allah gives you good tidings of John, confirming a word from Allah and [who will be] honorable, abstaining [from women],
وَسَيِّدًا وَحَصُورًا وَنَبِيًّا مِّنَ الصَّالِحِينَ - 3:39
and [who will be] honorable, abstaining [from women], and a prophet from among the righteous."
قَالَ رَبِّ أَنَّىٰ يَكُونُ لِي غُلَامٌ وَقَدْ بَلَغَنِيَ الْكِبَرُ وَامْرَأَتِي عَاقِرٌ ۖ
He said, "My Lord, how will I have a boy when I have reached old age and my wife is barren?"
قَالَ كَذَٰلِكَ اللَّهُ يَفْعَلُ مَا يَشَاءُ - 3:40
The angel said, "Such is Allah ; He does what He wills."
قَالَ رَبِّ اجْعَل لِّي آيَةً ۖ
He said, "My Lord, make for me a sign
قَالَ آيَتُكَ أَلَّا تُكَلِّمَ النَّاسَ ثَلَاثَةَ أَيَّامٍ إِلَّا رَمْزًا ۗ
He Said, "Your sign is that you will not [be able to] speak to the people for three days except by gesture.
وَاذْكُر رَّبَّكَ كَثِيرًا وَسَبِّحْ بِالْعَشِيِّ وَالْإِبْكَارِ - 3:41
And remember your Lord much and exalt [Him with praise] in the evening and the morning."